<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902"
    docName="draft-beeram-mpls-rsvp-te-scaling-00" obsoletes=""
    updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Improving RSVP-TE scalability">Improving RSVP-TE
        scalability - Recommendations</title>
    <author initials="V." surname="Beeram"
        fullname="Vishnu Pavan Beeram" role="editor">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <email>vbeeram@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="I." surname="Minei" fullname="Ina Minei">
      <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>inaminei@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="Y." surname="Rekhter" fullname="Yakov Rekhter">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94089</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>yakov@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="E." surname="Aries" fullname="Ebben Aries">
      <organization>Facebook</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1 Hacker Way</street>
          <city>Menlo Park</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94025</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>exa@fb.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Pacella" fullname="Dante Pacella">
      <organization>Verizon</organization>
      <address>
        <email>dante.j.pacella@verizon.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Jork" fullname="Markus Jork">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94089</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mjork@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2015"/>
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>RSVP</keyword>
    <keyword>MPLS</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
          RSVP-TE describes the use of standard RSVP to establish Label
          Switched Paths (LSPs).  As such, RSVP-TE inherited some
          properties of RSVP that adversely affect its control plane
          scalability.  Specifically these properties are (a) reliance
          on periodic refreshes for state synchronization between RSVP
          neighbors and for recovery from lost RSVP messages, (b)
          reliance on refresh timeout for stale state cleanup, and (c)
          lack of any mechanisms by which a receiver of RSVP messages
          can apply a back pressure to the sender(s) of these messages.
      </t>
      <t>
          Subsequent to RFC2205 and RFC3209 further enhancements to RSVP
          and RSVP-TE have been developed.  In this document we
          describe how an implementation of RSVP-TE can use these
          enhancements to address the above mentioned properties to
          improve RSVP-TE control plane scalability.
      </t>
    </abstract>
    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
        in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
      </t>
    </note>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro" toc="default">
      <t>
          <xref target="RFC3209">RSVP-TE</xref> describes the use of
          standard <xref target="RFC2205">RSVP</xref> to establish Label
          Switched Paths (LSPs).  As such, RSVP-TE inherited some
          properties of RSVP that adversely affect its control plane
          scalability.  Specifically these properties are (a) reliance
          on periodic refreshes for state synchronization between RSVP
          neighbors and for recovery from lost RSVP messages, (b)
          reliance on refresh timeout for stale state cleanup, and (c)
          lack of any mechanisms by which a receiver of RSVP messages
          can apply a back pressure to the sender(s) of these messages.
          The following elaborates on this.
      </t>
        <section title="Reliance on refreshes and refresh timeouts"
            toc="default">
            <t>
                Standard <xref target="RFC2205">RSVP</xref> maintains
                state via the generation of RSVP Path/Resv refresh
                messages.  Refresh messages are used to both synchronize
                state between RSVP neighbors and to recover from lost
                RSVP messages.  The use of refresh messages to cover
                many possible failures has resulted in two operational
                problems.  The first relates to scaling, the second
                relates to the reliability and latency of RSVP
                signaling.
            </t>
            <t>
                The scaling problem is linked to the control plane
                resource requirements of running RSVP-TE.  The resource
                requirements increase proportionally with the number of
                LSPs established by RSVP-TE.  Each such LSP requires the
                generation, transmission, reception and processing of
                RSVP Path and Resv messages per refresh period.
                Supporting a large number of LSPs and the corresponding
                volume of refresh messages, presents a scaling problem
                for the RSVP-TE control plane.
            </t>
            <t>
                The reliability and latency problem occurs when a
                triggered (non-refresh) RSVP messages such as Path,
                Resv, or PathTear is lost in transmission.  Standard
                <xref target="RFC2205">RSVP</xref> recovers from a lost
                message via RSVP refresh messages.  In the face of
                transmission loss of RSVP messages, the end-to-end
                latency of RSVP signaling, and thus the end-to-end
                latency of RSVP-TE signaled LSP establishment, is tied
                to the refresh interval of the Label Switch Routers(s)
                experiencing the loss.  When end-to-end signaling is
                limited by the refresh interval, the delay incurred in
                the establishement or the change of an RSVP-TE signaled
                LSP may be beyond the range of what is acceptable in
                practice.  This is because RSVP-TE ultimately controls
                establishment of the forwarding state required to
                realize RSVP-TE signaled LSPs.  Thus delay incurred in
                the establishment or the change of such LSPs results in
                delaying the data plane convergence, which in turn
                adversely impacts the services that rely on the data
                plane.
            </t>
            <t>
                One way to address the scaling problem caused by the
                refresh volume is to increase the refresh period, "R" as
                defined in Section 3.7 of <xref target="RFC2205"/>.
                Increasing the value of R provides linear improvement on
                RSVP-TE signaling overhead, but at the cost of
                increasing the time it takes to synchronize state.  For
                the reasons mentioned in the previous paragraph, in the
                context of RSVP-TE signaled LSPs increasing the time to
                synchronize state is not an acceptable option.
            </t>
            <t>
                One way to address the reliability and latency of RSVP
                signaling is to decrease the refresh period R.
                Decreasing the value of R increases the probability that
                state will be installed in the face of message loss, but
                at the cost of increasing refresh message rate and
                associated processing requirements, which in turn
                adversely affects RSVP-TE control plane scalability.
            </t>
            <t>
                An additional problem is the time to clean up the stale
                state after a tear message is lost.  RSVP does not
                retransmit ResvTear or PathTear messages.  If the sole
                tear message transmitted is lost, the stale state will
                only be cleaned up once the refresh timeout has expired.
                This may result in resources associated with the stale
                state being allocated for an unneccesary period of time.
                Note that even when the refresh period is adjusted, the
                refresh timeout must still expire since tear messages
                are not retransmitted.  Decreasing the refresh timeout
                by decresing the refresh interval will speed up timely
                stale state cleanup, but at the cost of increasing
                refresh message rate, which in turn adversely affects
                RSVP-TE control plane scalability.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Lack of back pressure" toc="default">
            <t>
                In standard RSVP and RSVP speaker sends RSVP messages to
                a peer with no regard for whether the peer's RSVP
                control plane is busy.  There is no control plane
                mechanism by which an RSVP speaker may apply back
                pressure to the peer - "ask" the peer to reduce the rate
                of rsvp messages that the peer sends to the speaker.
                RSVP-TE inherited this from standard RSVP.  Lack of such
                mechanism could result in RSVP-TE control plane
                congestion.
            </t>
            <t>
                RSVP-TE control plane is especially susceptible to
                congestion during link/node failures, as such failures
                produce bursts of RSVP-TE messages: Path/Resv for
                re-routing LSPs affected by the failures, Path/Resv for
                setup of new backup LSPs (as required by RSVP-TE Fast
                Reroute <xref target="RFC4090"/>), Tear/Error messages
                for the affected LSPs.  Note that the load on the
                RSVP-TE control plane caused by these bursts is in
                addition to the load due to the periodic refreshes of
                Path/Resv messages for the LSPs not affected by the
                failures.
            </t>
            <t>
                RSVP-TE control plane congestion may result in losses of
                RSVP messages, which in turn have detrimental effects on
                the overall system behavior.  Path/Resv refreshes lost
                by a peer's busy control plane will cause refresh
                timeout for some or all of its existing RSVP-TE state on
                the peer, thus inadvertently deleting existing LSPs and
                disrupting traffic carried over these LSPs.  Triggered
                Path/Resv lost by a peer's busy control plane may result
                in failure to establish new backup LSPs used by RSVP-TE
                Fast Reroute <xref target="RFC4090"/> before the state
                for the corresponding protected primary LSPs times out,
                thus defeating the whole purpose of RSVP-TE Fast
                Reroute.
            </t>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Recomendations" toc="default">
      <t>
          Subsequent to the publication of <xref target="RFC2205"/> and
          <xref target="RFC3209"/> further enhancements to RSVP and
          RSVP-TE have been developed.  In this section we describe how
          these enhancements could be used to address the problems
          listed in Section 1.
      </t>
      <section title="Eliminating reliance on refreshes and refresh
          timeouts" toc="default">
          <t>
              To eliminate reliance on refreshes for both state
              synchronization between RSVP neighbors and for recovery
              from lost RSVP messages, as well as to address both the
              refresh volume and the reliability issues with RSVP
              mechanisms other than adjusting refresh rate, this
              document RECOMMENDS the following:
              <list style="symbols">
                  <t>
                      Implement reliable delivery of Path/Resv messages
                      using the procedures specified in <xref
                          target="RFC2961"/>.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                      Indicate support for RSVP Refresh Overhead
                      Reduction Extensions (as specified in Section 2 of
                      <xref target="RFC2961"/> by default, with the
                      ability to override the default via configuration.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                      Make the value of the refresh interval
                      configurable with the default value of 20 minutes.
                  </t>
              </list>
          </t>
          <t>
              To eliminate reliance on refresh timeouts, in addtion to
              the above, this document RECOMMENDS the following:
              <list style="symbols">
                  <t>
                      Implement reliable delivery of Tear/Err messages
                      using the procedures specified in <xref
                          target="RFC2961"/>.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                      Implement coupling the state of individual LSPs
                      with the state of the corresponding RSVP-TE
                      signaling adjacency.  When and RSVP-TE speaker
                      detects RSVP-TE signaling adjacency failure, the
                      speaker MUST clean up the LSP state for all LSPs
                      affected by the failed adjacency.  The LSP state
                      is the combination of "path state" maintained as
                      Path State Block and "reservation state"
                      maintained as Reservation State Block (see Section
                      2.1 of <xref target="RFC2205"/>).
                  </t>
                  <t>
                      Use of Node-ID based Hello session (<xref
                          target="RFC3209"/>, <xref target="RFC4558"/>)
                      for detection of RSVP-TE signaling adjacency
                      failures.  Make the value of the node hello
                      interval <xref target="RFC3209"/> configurable;
                      increase the default value from 5ms (as specified
                      in Section 5.3 of <xref target="RFC3209"/> to 9
                      seconds.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                      Implement Procedures specified in <xref
                          target="I-D.chandra-mpls-enhanced-frr-bypass"/>
                      which describes methods to facilitate FRR that
                      works independently of the refresh-interval.
                  </t>
              </list>
          </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Providing the ability to apply back pressure"
          toc="default">
          <t>
              To provide an RSVP speaker with the ability to apply back
              pressure to its peer(s) to reduce/eliminate RSVP-TE
              control plane congestions, in addition to the above, this
              document RECOMMENDS the following:
              <list style="symbols">
                  <t>
                      Use lack of ACKs from a peer as an indication of
                      peer's RSVP-TE control plane congestion, in which
                      case the local system SHOULD throttle RSVP-TE
                      messages to the affected peer.  This has to be
                      done on a per-peer basis.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                      Retransmit of all RSVP-TE messages using
                      exponential backoff, as specified in Section 6 of
                      <xref target="RFC2961"/>.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                      Increase the Retry Limit (Rl), as defined in
                      Section 6.2 of <xref target="RFC2961"/>, from 3 to
                      7.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                      Prioritize Tear/Error over trigger Path/Resv sent
                      to a peer when the local system detects RSVP-TE
                      control plane congestion in the peer.
                  </t>
              </list>
          </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Making Acknowledgements mandatory" toc="default">
          <t>
              The reliable message delivery mechanism specified in <xref
                  target="RFC2961"/> states that "Nodes receiving a
              non-out of order message containing a MESSAGE_ID object
              with the ACK_Desired flag set, SHOULD respond with a
              MESSAGE_ID_ACK object".  To improve predictability of the
              system in terms of reliable message delivery this document
              RECOMMENDS that nodes receiving a non-out of order message
              containing a MESSAGE_ID object with the ACK_Desired flag
              set, MUST respond with a MESSAGE_ID_ACK object.
          </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Clarifications on reaching Rapid Retry Limit (Rl)"
          toc="default">
          <t>
              According to section 6 of <xref target="RFC2961"/> "The
              staged retransmission will continue until either an
              appropriate MESSAGE_ID_ACK object is received, or the
              rapid retry limit, Rl, has been reached".  The following
              clarifies what actions, if any, a router should take once
              Rl has been reached.
          </t>
          <t>
              If it is the retransmission of Tear/Err messages and Rl
              has been reached, the router need not take any further
              actions.
          </t>
          <t>
              If it is the retransmission of Path/Resv messages and Rl
              has been reached, then the router starts periodic
              retransmission of these messages every 30 seconds.  The
              retransmitted messages MUST carry MESSAGE_ID object with
              ACK_Desired flag set.  This periodic retransmission SHOULD
              continue until an appropriate MESSAGE_ID ACK object is
              received indicating acknowledgement of the (retransmitted)
              Path/Resv message.
          </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Avoiding use of Router Alert IP Option"
          toc="default">
          <t>
              In RSVP-TE the Path message is carried in an IP packet
              that is addressed to the tail end of the LSP that is
              signaled using this message.  To make all the
              intermediate/transit LSRs process this message, the IP
              packet carrying the message includes the Router Alert IP
              option.  The same applies to the PathTear message.
          </t>
          <t>
              An alternative to relying on the Router Alert IP option is
              to carry the Path or PathTear message as a sub-message of
              a Bundle message <xref target="RFC2961"/>, as Bundle
              messages are "addressed directly to RSVP neighbors" and
              "SHOULD NOT be sent with the Router Alert IP option in
              their IP headers" <xref target="RFC2961"/>.  Notice that
              since a Bundle message could contain only a single
              sub-message, this approach could be used to send just a
              single Path or PathTear message.  This document RECOMMENDS
              implementing support for Bundle messages <xref
                  target="RFC2961"/>, and carrying Path and PathTear
              message(s) as sub-messages(s) of a Bundle message.
          </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Checking Data Plane readiness" toc="default">
          <t>
              In certain scenarios, like Make-Before-Break (MBB), a
              router needs to move traffic from an existing LSP to a new
              LSP in a least disruptive fashion.  To accomplish this the
              data plane of the new LSP must be operational before the
              router moves the traffic.
          </t>
          <t>
              A possible mechanism by which the router can determine
              whether the data plane of the new LSP is operational is
              specified in <xref
                  target="I-D.bonica-mpls-self-ping"/>.  This
              document RECOMMENDS implementing this mechanism and using
              it whenever the ingress of an LSP needs to check whether
              the data plane of the LSP is operational.
          </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>
          This document makes no request of IANA.
      </t>
      <t>
          Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication
          as an RFC.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations" toc="default">
        <t>
            This document does not introduce new security issues.  The
            security considerations pertaining to the original RSVP
            protocol <xref target="RFC2205"/> and RSVP-TE <xref
                target="RFC3209"/> remain relevant.
        </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements" toc="default">
        <t>
            Most of the text in Section 1.1 has been taken almost
            verbatim from <xref target="RFC2961"/>.
        </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2205.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2961.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3209.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4090.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4558.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.I-D.bonica-mpls-self-ping"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.I-D.chandra-mpls-enhanced-frr-bypass"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
